Finding Aid for Madison Foster Papers, 1969-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Madison Foster Papers 1969-1970
Foster, Madison, 1940-
1 linear ft.
Student at the University of Michigan, later lecturer in social work, and active member of the League of Revolutionary Black Workers (LRBW). Materials relating to the Black Action Movement (BAM) strike at the University of Michigan in 1970; papers detailing his involvement with the LRBW, the International Black Appeal (IBA), and other black organizations.
85165 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection came from Mr. Foster (donor no. 6566 ) in 1981.
The collection is open for research.
Madison James Foster was a African-American author, teacher, and activist whose career spanned a wide range of political and intellectual pursuits. Born in Louisiana in 1940, Foster attended Morehouse College, center of early civil rights activity. In 1963 he came to the University of Michigan School of Social Work as a graduate student. After spending several years studying in Europe he returned to Michigan as a faculty member, and involved himself in two highly significant organizations: the League of Revolutionary Black Workers in Detroit, and the Black Action Movement at the University of Michigan.
From 1969 through 1972 Foster was an active member of the League of Revolutionary Black Workers. Organized by a group of Detroit's most dynamic activists, the League challenged the automobile companies and the United Auto Workers union hierarchy with outspoken propaganda and militant wildcat strikes. Though less flamboyant than the Black Panthers, the League was certainly one of the most serious and well-organized political groups of its time.
While involved in the League, Foster also took part in the highly controversial Black Action Movement strike of March, 1970. As a strategist and negotiator, he helped BAM win unprecedented concessions from the University of Michigan administration. In the opinion of many experts, the 13-day BAM strike was one of the most successful student strikes of the Vietnam era.
Foster was also active in 1971 in organizing the Ann Arbor chapter of the International Black Appeal (IBA), a funding organization developed to address the particular needs of the black community.
Madison Foster's papers document some of the most important currents of black activism of the 1960s and early 1970s, and provide a unique insight into the history of this period. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Black Action Movement; League of Revolutionary Black Workers; International Black Appeal; and Topical Files.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); Foster, Madison, 1940-; International Black Appeal.; League of Revolutionary Black Workers.; Radicalism--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.
- Black Action Movement (BAM)
  Foster's files on the Black Action Movement contain rare memorandums, negotiating notes, press releases, clippings, and commentary on the strike.
  - Pre-BAM: Blacks at U-M, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - BAM Strike
    - Undated and February 17-March 20, 1970 (Box 1)
    - March 23-28, 1970 (Box 1)
    - March 29-April 2, 1970 (Box 1)
  - BAM Strike (aftermath)
    - April 1970-March 1971 (Box 1)
    - June 1971-February 1980 (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - 1969-March 1970 (Box 1)
    - April 1-14, 1970 (Box 1)
    - April 17, 1970-March 1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1980 (Box 1)
- League of Revolutionary Black Workers (LRBW)
  Foster's League of Revolutionary Black Workers papers include correspondence, meeting minutes, periodicals, and League position papers. One of the most important documents is the Program of the League, which details explicitly the structure, ideology, and policies of this dynamic organization.
  - LRBW Program, July 1970 (Box 1)
  - Statements of policy (Box 1)
  - Meeting notices, 1969-1972 and Foster's letter of resignation, January 1972 (Box 1)
  - Scandinavian trip, 1971
    - Correspondence, February 1971-February 1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Itinerary, interview with Foster, and miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Danish pamphlets and clippings (Box 1)
  - Black Workers' Congress (Box 1)
  - Split in League, July 1971 (Box 1)
  - John Watson interviews, 1969 and 1970 (Box 1)
  - James Johnson trial (Box 1)
  - New Bethel Defense Fund (Box 1)
  - Publications
    - DRUM pamphlets and articles (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous publications and broadsides (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- International Black Appeal (IBA)
  The International Black Appeal (IBA) series includes useful material on the rationale and purposes of the IBA and on the July 1971 Ann Arbor Blues Recital which was organized by the IBA.
  - Rationale and objectives (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor chapter
    - Establishment (Box 1)
    - Budget and committees (Box 1)
    - United Fund (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Blues Recital, July 1971
      - General (Box 1)
      - Interviews (Box 1)
    - General and miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Topical files
  - Ann Arbor public schools boycott, November 1971 (Box 1)
  - Black Manifesto (Box 1)
  - Black Political Seminar (Box 1)
  - Black Student Union (Box 1)
  - Center for Afro-American and African Studies (Box 1)
  - People United for Community Service (Box 1)
  - School of Social Work, University of Michigan (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)